A Finding Aid to the Martin H. Bush Papers, 1948-2012, bulk 1970- 2008, in the Archives of American Art aaa.bushmart
Archives of American Art
Martin H. Bush papers
bulk 1970-2008
1948-2012
aaa.bushmart
Archives of American Art
4.1 Linear feet
The papers of Martin H. Bush measure 4.1 linear feet and date from 1948-2012, with the bulk of the material dating from 1970-2008. The collection documents Bush's career as an art historian, educator, consultant, and gallery director through biographical material, correspondence, interviews, subject files, a scrapbook, and printed material.
Bush, Martin H.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1956-2008 (Box1, OV 5; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1984-2012 (Box 1; 0.8 linear ft.)
Series 3: Interviews, circa 1970-1994 (Boxes 1-2; 1 linear ft.)
Series 4: Subject Files, 1963-2012 (Boxes 2-4; 2 linear ft.)
Series 5: Scrapbook, 1971-2000 (Box 4; 1 folder)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1948, 1964-circa 2000 (Box 4, 0.25 linear ft.)
Biographical/Historical note
Martin H. Bush (1932-) is an art historian, educator, consultant, and gallery director.
Bush received a Bachelor of Arts from the State University of New York at Albany in 1958. From 1963-1965, he taught at Syracuse University, where he earned his Ph.D in History in 1966. Bush also served as the University's Assistant Dean for Academic Resources from 1965-1970. During this time, Martin H. Bush was also a consultant to the New York State Education Department.
From 1970-1974, Martin H. Bush was the Vice President of Academic Resource Development at Wichita State University, a position created for him by the University's President, Clark Ahlberg. In this post, Bush established a special collections department at Ablah Library and the Ulrich Museum of Art. Bush was also a consultant to several major corporations in Wichita, including Fourth Financial Corporation, Range Oil Company, and American Diversified Real Estate. In 1974, in recognition of Bush's contribution to the museum, the University opened the Martin H. Bush Outdoor Sculpture Collection. Bush has been involved in the acquisition of major pieces of outdoor sculpture from such well-known artists as Chaim Gross, Barbara Hepworth, Henry Moore, Juan Miró, Louise Nevelson, and George Rickey. In 1989, Bush moved to New York City, where he continued his work as an art consultant. From 1992-1993, he was President of the ACA Gallery.
Martin H. Bush has published many books and articles on artists as well as contributed essays for exhibition catalogs. In the 1970s-1980s, Bush interviewed major artists for public television and radio programs in Wichita, among them Benny Andrews, Isabel Bishop, Richard Pousette-Dart, and Theodoros Stamos. Martin H. Bush's honors and awards include the George S. Patton Medal by the government of Luxembourg for his essay, "Ben Shahn: The Passion of Sacco and Vanzetti," 1969; "Outstanding Educator" by the Kansas Art Education Association, 1979; and the Wichita Arts Council Award, 1984.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original material requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 2013 by Martin H. Bush.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Martin H. Bush measure 4.1 linear feet and date from 1948-2012, with the bulk of the material dating from 1970-2008. The collection documents Bush's career as an art historian, educator, consultant, and gallery director through biographical material, correspondence, interviews, subject files, a scrapbook, and printed material.
Biographical material includes curriculum vitae, a certificate of discharge from the United States Army Reserve, and a lifetime membership certificate from the Edwin A. Ulrich Museum of Art. Most of the correspondence is personal in nature and consists of letters between Bush and his colleagues at Wichita State University and the Ulrich Museum of Art, friends, and family members. Martin H. Bush's interviews on videocassette with artists and other figures in the art world include Benny Andrews, Duane Hanson, Ivan Karp, Alice Neel, Louise Nevelson, and Arnold Newman.
Subject files primarily document Martin H. Bush's activities as an art dealer and consultant and contain auction house sales and files on individual artists, including Richard Pousette-Dart, Robert Goodnough, Ernest Trova, and Isaac Witkin. Source files include illustrated letters by John Von Wicht and a folder on Samuel Beckett's correspondence with Bush that includes three holograph letters and one typescript letter from Beckett. A small amount of material references Bush's tenure as director of the ACA Gallery. Photographic materials are also included.
A scrapbook contains news clippings and excerpts of newsletters covering Bush's career at Wichita State University. Printed material includes books, an educational brochure, exhibition catalogs, and a memorial booklet.
ACA Galleries.; Andrews, Benny, 1930-2006; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989; Edwin A. Ulrich Museum of Art.; Goodnough, Robert, 1917-; Hanson, Duane; Karp, Ivan C., 1926-2012; Neel, Alice, 1900-1984; Nevelson, Louise, 1899-1988; Newman, Arnold, 1918-2006; Pousette-Dart, Richard, 1916-1992; Trova, Ernest T., 1927-; Von Wicht, John, 1888-1970; Wichita State University. -- Faculty; Witkin, Isaac; Art historians; Art--Study and teaching; Consultants; Educators; Gallery directors; Interviews; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Video recordings
- Biographical Material, 1956-2008; Series 1; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1, OV 5
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes a certificate of discharge from the United State Army Reserve, a membership certificate from the Edwin A. Ulrich Museum of Art, and a clipping detailing the significant artwork acquired by Bush for the Ulrich Museum. Biographical information provides an overview of Bush's professional activities and accomplishments as a consultant, an university arts administrator, educator, and art historian.
  Arrangement note
  Biographical material is arranged by subject.
  - Biographical Information, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificate of Discharge from the United States Army Reserve, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lifetime Membership Certificate from the Edwin A. Ulrich Museum of Art, Wichita State University (1992 January 24) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Oversized material housed in Box 5
  - Clipping about Martin H. Bush, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Certificate from the Edwin A. Ulrich Museum of Art, Wichita State University (1992 January 24), from Box 1, Folder 3 (Box OV 5)
- Correspondence, 1984-2012; Series 2; 0.8 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence reflects Bush's activities as an independent consultant. Files also contain curriculum vitae, printed material, brochures, clippings, and appraisal of artwork. Correspondents include colleagues at Wichita State University, museum directors, curators, collectors, and friends. Letters between Bush and his friends discuss baseball, particularly Bush's interest in early twentieth century baseball players. Of interest, is correspondence between Martin H. Bush and Lois More Overbeck, co-editor of The Letters of Samuel Beckett; Overbeck was seeking permission to reprint the letters between Bush and Samuel Beckett. Also included are letters from Bush's wife, Jennie.
  Correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order. Names with five or more letters are filed alphabetically by person or corporate name.
  - Correspondence, A, undated; 2007 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes letters from Clark Ahlberg
  - Correspondence, B, 2002-2009 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Burke, Jim, 2002-2009 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Bush, Jennie, undated; 1998-2012 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Bush, Martin H., 2000-2011; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, C-E, undated; 2002-2011 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, G, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, H-J, 2000-2009 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, K-M, 1995-2005 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, O-P, 1995-2009 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, Piskor, Frank P., undated; 1998-2006 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Platt, George M., undated; 2000-2012 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, R-S, 1996-2011; undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, T-U, undated; 2000-2010 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Includes a thank you note from Ernest Trova
  - Correspondence, W-Y, undated; 1999-2012 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence without Surnames, undated; 1984-2008 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Interviews, circa 1970-1994; Series 3; 1 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  This series consists of Bush's interviews with artists and prominent figures in the art world. Some of the interviews by Bush were conducted during his tenure as Director of the Ulrich Museum. Interviews are recorded on 12 videocassettes; some videorecordings include multiple interviews.
  Additional interviews can also be found in Series 4: Subject Files. This series is arranged in chronological order.
  - Ulrich Museum of Tapes
    - List of Ulrich Museum Tapes, circa 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "A Conversation with Ivan Karp", circa 1970-circa 1980; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Includes interviews with Benny Andrews, Arnold Newman, and Duane Hanson
    - "A Visit with Richard McLean," Tape 4, circa 1970-circa 1980; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - "The Discovery of Alice Neel," Tape 5, circa 1970-circa 1980; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Includes interview with Louise Nevelson, "Born Artist"
    - Richard Anuzkiewicz (1975 October), Tape 7, 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "Visiting Artist Gallo", circa 1980-circa 1990; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - "Visiting Artist Ernst Neizvestny", circa 1980-circa 1990; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "An Interview with Philip Reisman", circa 1980-circa 1990; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "Weston Photographs: Three Generations, An Interview with Cole Weston", circa 1980-circa 1990; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - NBC Interviews with Carole Feuerman (1994 May 12), 2 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - R. H. Love Galleries, "American Art Forum" (1994 August 10), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Subject Files, 1963-2012; Series 4; 2 Linear feet Boxes 2-4
  This series includes files on Martin H. Bush's dealings with individual artists, mostly relating to exhibitions, some organized by Martin H. Bush and sales of artwork. There are extensive files on Richard Pousette-Dart, Robert Goodnough, Ernest Trova, and Isaac Witkin. Auction files document Bush's consulting projects for art institutions, such as Owensboro Museum of Art and the Ulrich Museum of Art as well as his activities as a collector. Files may include a variety of material, such as correspondence, drafts, memoranda, proposals, informational sheets, lists of artwork, inventory lists, condition reports, printed material, clippings and reviews, exhibition catalogs, annotated auction catalogs, and photographic materials, including slides and transparencies. Among the business-related materials are appraisals, price lists, sale sheets, bids, lists of deaccessioned artwork, consignment agreements, condition reports, receipts, and invoices. There is limited documentation relating to Bush's directorship at ACA Gallery.
  Also found are Martin H. Bush's correspondence with Samuel Beckett, including three holograph letters and one typescript letter from Beckett; John Von Wicht's illustrated letters; and an annotated typescript of Bush's account of his initial meeting with Joan Miró. Other source files include a list of scholars conducting research for catalogue raisonné projects, obituary notices on friends and acquaintances, and the Ulrich Museum of Art, particularly the museum's twentieth-fifth anniversary celebration. Two videorecordings of an ESPN "Up Close" Interview and and ESPN Hall of Fame induction ceremony reflect Bush's interest in baseball.
  Subject files include 11 videocassettes and 1 electronic disc (DVD).
  Files are arranged by subject and thereafter in alphabetical order.
  - Artists
    - Anuszkiewicz, Richard, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Goodnough, Robert
      - Correspondence, undated; 1973-2007 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - ACA Gallery, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Articles and Clippings, undated; 1981-2010 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
      - "A Day with Robert Goodnough," Fashion Institute of Technology, circa 1990s; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - "Dinosaurs Visit the Stamford Museum" and "Installation of Steel Sculpture, Mt. Kisco, New York", circa 1990s; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - "Goodnough, Paintings and Sculpture", circa 1990s; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Interview at the Museum of Modern Art, circa 1990s; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Writings, circa 2000-2004 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Photographic Images, 2000s (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    - Hanson, Duane, 1996-2009 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Hayes, David, 2005-2007 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Kearney, John, 2005-2007 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Klitgaard, Georgina, 1970; 2004-2009 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Miró, Joan, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Nichols, Dale, 2004-2012 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Pousette-Dart, Richard, 1990-1993; Includes a discussion on Richard Pousette-Dart recorded on 1 videocassette (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Reginato, Peter, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Rickey, George - Sculptures, circa 1980-circa 1990; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Rosenthal, Doris, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Trova, Ernest, 2008-2010 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Trova, Ernest - Trova vs. Universal Sewing Supply, 1987-1995 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Von Wicht, John, 1963-2005 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Witkin, Isaac, 1988; 2005-2007 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Witkin, Isaac - Claim Against the Estate, 2006-2008 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Auctions
    - Art Dealer Association, 2001-2005 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Bunte Auction Services, 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 14-19)
    - Fairfield Auction, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Freeman's Auction House, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - James Di Julia's Auction, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - John McGinnis Auctioneer, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Northeast Auctions, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Shannon's, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Skinner, Inc. - Ernest Trova, 2005-2008 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Stair Galleries, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Stanton Enterprises, 2005-2007 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Swann Auction Galleries, circa 2005 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Thomaston Place Auction Galleries, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Vallot Fine Art Auctioneers, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Weschler's Auctioneers and Appraisers, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Miscellaneous Inventory Lists, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Beckett, Samuel, 1963-1969; 2008 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Bush, Martin H. - Lists of Artwork and Clipping, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Coutts Memorial Museum of Art, 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - ESPN "Up Close" Interview with David Cone and ESPN's Hall of Fame Induction Ceremony, 1999; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - List of Scholars/Catalogues Raisonné, 2000s (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Obituaries - "Friends and Acquaintances", circa 1998-2012; Includes 1 electronic disc (DVD) (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Obituaries - "People I Have Known", 1996-2012 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Owensboro, Kentucky - Mary Brian Hood, 2005-2007 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Simon Parkes Art Conservation, Inc., 2002-2008 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Tatti - Sculpture Conservator, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Ulrich Museum of Art, 1974-2011 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - Ulrich Museum of Art - Archives Inventory, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Ulrich Museum of Art - Twenty-Five Years Celebration, 1992-2007 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Scrapbook, 1971-2000; Series 5; 1 Folders Box 4
  A scrapbook of news clippings provides an account of Bush's activities and accomplishments at the Ulrich Museum of Art. Also found are two letters and a few photographs.
  Although the volume has been dismantled, its original order is retained.
  - Scrapbook, 1971-2000 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Printed Material, 1964-circa 2000; 1948; Series 6; 0.25 Linear feet Box 4
  The small amount of printed material in the collection includes a book of biographical entries on artists, exhibition catalogs, and a memorial booklet on Philip Reisman. Included are inscribed publications, two from Abraham Walkowitz and one from Kenzo Okada. An educational brochure, The Birth of a Song by Martin H. Bush provides historical background to the writing of "The Star Spangled Banner."
  AThis series is arranged by format.
  - Book, Improvisations of New York: A Symphony in Lines, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Book, Art: From Life to Life, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Book, World Artists, 1950-1980, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Booklet, The Birth of a Song, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Memorial Booklet, Philip Reisman: A Life Remembered, 1904-1992, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Exhibition Catalog, Huntertwass Erfriedereich, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Exhibition Catalog, Kenzo Okada Paintings, 1931-1965 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition Catalog, Architektur Der Hoffnung: Natur und Menschen Gerechteres Wohnen, circa 1990-circa 2000 (Box 4, Folder 19)